在这段视频中我想谈谈正规方程 ( normal equation )
(字幕整理：中国海洋大学 黄海广,haiguang2000@qq.com )
In this video, I want to talk about the normal equation
以及它们的不可逆性
and non-invertibility.
尽管是一种较为深入的概念
This is a somewhat more advanced concept,
但总有人问我有关这方面的问题
but it is something that I've often been asked about.
因此 我想在这里来讨论它
And so I wanted to talk about it here.
由于概念较为深入
But this is a somewhat more advanced concept,
所以对这段可选材料大家放轻松吧
so feel free to consider this optional material
下面
There's a phenomenon that you may run into
举一个比较实用的例子
that's maybe for some of you useful to understand.
这是一个关于正规方程和线性回归的例子
But even if you don't understand it,
即使你没能理解
the normal equation and linear regression,
也没有关系
you should really get that to work okay.
问题如下
Here's the issue:
你或许可能对
For those of you that are maybe somewhat
线性代数比较熟悉
more familar with linear algebra,
有些同学曾经问过我
what some students have asked me is,
当计算
when computing this
θ等于inv(X'X ) X'y （注：X的转置翻译为X'，下同）
theta equals ( Xtranspose X )inverse Xtranspose y
那对于矩阵X'X的结果是不可逆的情况呢?
what if the matrix Xtranspose X is non-invertible?
如果你懂一点线性代数的知识
So, for those of you that know a bit more linear algebra
你或许会知道
you may know that only some matrices
有些矩阵可逆 而有些矩阵不可逆
are invertible and some matrices do not have an inverse
我们称那些不可逆矩阵为
we call those non-invertible matrices,
奇异或退化矩阵
singular or degenerate matrices.
问题的重点在于X'X的不可逆的问题
The issue or the problem of Xtranpose X being non-invertible
很少发生
should happen pretty rarely.
在Octave里 如果你用它来实现θ的计算
And in Octave, if you implement this to compute theta,
你将会得到正解
it turns out that this will actually do the right thing.
在这里我不想赘述
I'm getting a little bit technical now and I don't want to go into details,
在Octave里 有两个函数可以求解矩阵的逆
but Octave has two functions for inverting matrices:
一个被称为pinv ( ) 另一个是inv ( )
One is called pinv(), and the other is called inv().
这两者之间的差异是些许计算过程上的
The differences between these two are somewhat technical.
一个是所谓的伪逆 另一个被称为逆
One's called the pseudo-inverse, one's called the inverse.
使用pinv ( ) 函数可以展现数学上的过程
You can show mathemically so as long as you use the pinv() function,
这将计算出θ的值
then this will actually compute the value of theta that you want,
即便矩阵X'X是不可逆的
even if Xtranspose X is non-invertible.
在pinv ( ) 和 inv ( ) 之间
The specific details between what is the difference between
又有哪些具体区别 ?
pinv() and what is inv()
其中inv ( ) 引入了先进的数值计算的概念
that is somewhat advanced numerical computing concepts,
我真的不希望讲那些
that I don't really want to get into.
因此 我认为
But I thought in this optional
可以试着给你一点点直观的参考
video I try to give you a little bit of intuition
关于矩阵X'X的不可逆的问题
about what it means that Xtranspose X to be non-invertible.
如果你懂一点线性代数
For those of you that know a bit more linear algebra
或许你可能会感兴趣
and might be interested.
我不会从数学的角度来证明它
I'm not going to proove this mathematically,
但如果矩阵X'X结果是不可逆的
but if Xtranspose X is non-invertible,
通常有两种最常见的原因
there are usually two most common causes:
第一个原因是 如果不知何故 在你的学习问题
The first cause is if somehow, in your learning problem,
你有多余的功能
you have redundant features,
例如 在预测住房价格时
concretely, if you try to predict housing prices
如果x1是以英尺为尺寸规格计算的房子
and if x1 is the size of a house in square-feet,
x2是以平方米为尺寸规格计算的房子
and x2 is the size of the house in square-meters,
同时 你也知道1米等于3 28英尺 ( 四舍五入到两位小数 )
then, you know, 1 meter is equal to 3.28 feet, rounded to two decimals,
这样 你的这两个特征值将始终满足约束
and so your two features will always satisfy the constraint
x1等于x2倍的3.28平方
that x1 equals 3(.28)^2 times x2.
并且你可以将这过程显示出来 讲到这里 可能 或许对你来说有点难了
And you can show, for those of you - this is somehwat advanced linear algebra now,
但如果你在线性代数上非常熟练
but if you're an expert in linear algebra,
实际上 你可以用这样的一个线性方程 来展示那两个相关联的特征值
you can actually show that if your two features are related via a linear equation like this,
矩阵X'X将是不可逆的
then matrix Xtranspose X will be non-invertible.
第二个原因是 在你想用大量的特征值
The second thing that can cause Xtranspose X to be non-invertible
尝试实践你的学习算法的时候
is if you're trying to run a learning algorithm
可能会导致矩阵X'X的结果是不可逆的
with a lot of a features.
具体地说 在m小于或等于n的时候
Concretely, if m is less than or equal to n.
例如 有m等于10个的训练实例
For example, if you imagine that you have m equals 10 training examples
也有n等于100的特征数量
and that you have n equals 100 features, then you're trying
要找到适合的 ( n +1 ) 维参数矢量θ 这是第
to fit a parameter vector theta, which is (n+1)-dimensional,
这将会变成一个101维的矢量
so it's a 101-dimensional
尝试从10个训练实例中找到满足101个参数的值
you're trying to fit a 101 parameters from just 10 training examples.
这工作可能会让你花上一阵子时间
And this turns out to sometimes work,
但这并不总是一个好主意
but to not always be a good idea.
因为 正如我们所看到 你只有10个例子 以适应这100或101个参数
Because, as we see later, you might not have enough data
数据还是有些少
if you only have 10 examples to fit 100 or 101 parameters.
稍后我们将看到
We'll see later in this course, why this might be too little data
如何使用小数据样本以得到这100或101个参数
to fit this many parameters.
通常 我们会使用一种叫做正则化的线性代数方法
But commonly, what we do then if m is less than n,
通过删除某些特征或者是使用某些技术
is to see if we can either delete some features or to use a technique
来解决当m比n小的时候的问题
called regularization,
这也是在本节课后面要讲到的内容
which is something that we will talk about a bit later in this course as well,
即使你有一个相对较小的训练集
that will kind of let you fit a lot of parameters using a lot of features
也可使用很多的特征来找到很多合适的参数
even if you have a relatively small training set.
有关正规化的内容将是本节之后课程的话题
But this regularization will be a later topic in this course.
总之当你发现的矩阵X'X的结果是奇异矩阵
But to summarize, if ever you find that Xtranspose X is singular
或者找到的其它矩阵是不可逆的
or alternatively find is non-invertible,
我会建议你这么做
what I would recommend you do is
首先 看特征值里是否有一些多余的特征
first: look at your features and see if you have redundant features
像这些x1和x2是线性相关的
like these x1 and x2 being linearly dependent,
或像这样 互为线性函数
or being a linear function of each other, like so
同时 当有一些多余的特征时
and if you do have redundant features and
可以删除这两个重复特征里的其中一个
if you just delete one of these features -
无须两个特征同时保留
you really don't need both of these features,
所以 发现多余的特征删除二者其一
so if you just delete one of these features
将解决不可逆性的问题
that will solve your non-invertibility problem
因此 首先应该通过观察所有特征检查是否有多余的特征
and, so first think through my features and check if any are redundant
如果有多余的就删除掉
and if so, then, you know, keep deleting the redundant features
直到他们不再是多余的为止
until they are no longer redundant.
如果特征里没有多余的
And if your features are non redundant,
我会检查是否有过多的特征
I would check if I might have too many features,
如果特征数量实在太多
and if that's the case I would either
我会删除些 用较少的特征来反映尽可能多内容
delete some features if I can bare to use fewer features,
否则我会考虑使用正规化方法
or else I would consider using regularization,
这也是我们将要谈论的话题
which is this topic that we will talk about later.
同时 这也是有关标准方程的内容
So, that's it for the normal equation and what it means
如果矩阵X'X是不可逆的
if the matrix Xtranspose X is non-invertible.
通常来说 不会出现这种情况
But this is a problem that hopefully you run into pretty rarely.
如果在Octave里
And if you just implement it in Octave using the pinv() function
可以用伪逆函数pinv ( ) 来实现
which is called the pseudo-inverse function
这种使用不同的线性代数库的方法被称为伪逆
so you use a different linear algebra library, that is called pseudo-inverse
即使X'X的结果是不可逆的
but that implementation should just do the right thing
但算法执行的流程是正确的
even if Xtranspose X is non-invertible
总之 出现不可逆矩阵的情况极少发生
which should happen pretty rarily anyway
所以在大多数实现线性回归中 出现不可逆的问题不应该过多的关注
so this should not be a problem for most implementations of linear regression.